War has been a part of my life since I can remember.
كانت الحرب جزءًا من حياتي منذ ما أستطيع أن أتذكر.
I was born in Afghanistan, just six months after the Soviets invaded,
وُلدت بأفغنستان، ستة أشهر بعد الغزو السوفياتي
and even though I was too young to understand what was happening,
وبالرغم من أنني كنت ما أزال صغيرة لأفهم ما كان يجري،
I had a deep sense of the suffering and the fear around me.
فقد كان لدي شعور عميق بالمعاناة والخوف من حولي.
Those early experiences had a major impact on how I now think about war and conflict.
تلك التجارب المبكرة كان لها تأثير مهم على كيفية تفكيري بالحروب والصراعات الآن.
I learned that when people have a fundamental issue at stake,
تعلمت أنه عندما يكون للناس مسألة رئيسية على المحك،
for most of them,
فبالنسبة لمعظمهم،
giving in is not an option.
الاستسلام ليس خيارًا.
For these types conflicts --
بالنسبة لأنواع الصراعات هذه --
when people's rights are violated,
عندما تُنتهك حقوق الناس،
when their countries are occupied,
وتُحتل دولهم،
when they're oppressed and humiliated --
ويُقهرون ويذَلون --
they need a powerful way to resist and to fight back.
فهم في حاجة إلى طريقة قوية للمقاومة والرد.
Which means that no matter how destructive and terrible violence is,
ما يعني أنه مهما كان العنف مدمرًا أو رهيبًا،
if people see it as their only choice,
لو رآه الناس الخيار الوحيد،
they will use it.
فسيستعملونه.
Most of us are concerned with the level of violence in the world.
معظمنا قلق بشأن مستوى العنف في العالم.
But we're not going to end war
ولكننا لن ننهي الحرب
by telling people that violence is morally wrong.
بإخبار الناس أن العنف أخلاقيًا خطأ.
Instead, we must offer them a tool
بدلًا من ذلك، علينا أن نوفر لهم وسيلة
that's at least as powerful and as effective as violence.
بنفس قوة وفاعلية العنف على الأقل.
This is the work I do.
هذا ما أقوم به.
For the past 13 years,
على مدار الثلاث عشرة سنة الماضية،
I've been teaching people
علمت أناسًا
in some of the most difficult situations around the world
في أقصى الوضعيات صعوبة حول العالم
how they can use nonviolent struggle to conduct conflict.
كيف يمكنهم استخدام النضال السلمي من أجال إدارة الصراع.
Most people associate this type of action with Gandhi and Martin Luther King.
معظم الناس ينسبون هذا النوع من النضال إلى غاندي ومارتن لوثر كينج.
But people have been using nonviolent action for thousands of years.
لكن النضال السلمي يُستخدم منذ آلاف السنين.
In fact, most of the rights that we have today in this country --
في الواقع، معظم الحقوق التي نتمتع بها في هذا البلد --
as women,
كنساء،
as minorities,
وكأقليات،
as workers,
وكعمال،
as people of different sexual orientations
وكأناس ذوي توجهات جنسية مختلفة،
and citizens concerned with the environment --
وكمواطنين مهتمين بالبيئة --
these rights weren't handed to us.
فهذه الحقوق لم تُمنح لنا.
They were won by people who fought for them
بل اكتسبها أناسٌ ناضلوا من أجلها
and who sacrificed for them.
وضحّوا من أجلها.
But because we haven't learned from this history,
ولكن لأننا لم نقرأ ذلك في كتب التاريخ
nonviolent struggle as a technique is widely misunderstood.
فالنضال السلمي، كأسلوب، يُساء فهمه على نطاق واسع.
I met recently with a group of Ethiopian activists,
التقيت مؤخرًا بمجموعة من النشطاء الأثيوبيين،
and they told me something that I hear a lot.
وأخبروني عن شيء لطالما سمعتُ عنه.
They said they'd already tried nonviolent action,
قالوا أنهم حاولوا استخدام النضال السلمي،
and it hadn't worked.
ولم يجدِ نفعًا.
Years ago they held a protest.
منذ سنوات نظموا احتجاجًا.
The government arrested everyone, and that was the end of that.
فاعتقلت الحكومة الجميع، وكانت هذه نهاية القصة.
The idea that nonviolent struggle is equivalent to street protests
تعد فكرة أن النضال السلمي مساوية للاحتجاج في الشارع
is a real problem.
مشكلةً حقيقيةً.
Because although protests can be a great way to show that people want change,
فبالرغم من كون الاحتجاجات طريقة جيدة لإظهار رغبة الناس في التغيير،
on their own, they don't actually create change --
لكنها بمفردها لا تخلق تغييرًا --
at least change that is fundamental.
تغييرًا ضروريًا على الأقل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Powerful opponents are not going to give people what they want
الخصوم الأقوياء لن يمنحوا للشعب ما يريد
just because they asked nicely ...
لمجرد أنهم طالبوا بذلك بطريقة لبقة...
or even not so nicely.
أو حتى غير لبقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Nonviolent struggle works by destroying an opponent,
يعمل النضال السلمي عن طريق تدمير الخصم،
not physically,
ليس جسديًا،
but by identifying the institutions that an opponent needs to survive,
ولكن عن طريق تحديد المؤسسات التي يحتاجها الخصم للنجاة،
and then denying them those sources of power.
ومن ثَم حرمانهم من مصادر القوة هذه.
Nonviolent activists can neutralize the military
يمكن للمناضلين السلميين أن يُبطلوا مفعول الجيش
by causing soldiers to defect.
بأن يتسببوا في انشقاق الجنود عنه.
They can disrupt the economy through strikes and boycotts.
يمكنهم أن يُخلّوا بالاقتصاد عن طريق الاعتصامات والمقاطعات.
And they can challenge government propaganda
ويمكنهم أن يتحدوا دعاية الحكومة الكاذبة
by creating alternative media.
عن طريق خلق إعلام بديل.
There are a variety of methods that can be used to do this.
هناك طرق متعددة يمكن استخدامها من أجل ذلك.
My colleague and mentor, Gene Sharp,
زميلي ومعلمي، جين شارب،
has identified 198 methods of nonviolent action.
قد حدد 198 طريقة للنضال السلمي.
And protest is only one.
والاحتجاج هو مجرد واحد منها.
Let me give you a recent example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالًا حديثًا.
Until a few months ago,
حتى أشهر قليلة مضت
Guatemala was ruled by corrupt former military officials
كانت جواتيمالا محكومة من قبل مسؤولين عسكريين سابقين فاسدين
with ties to organized crime.
تربطهم علاقة بالجريمة المنظمة.
People were generally aware of this,
كان الناس عامةً على وعي بهذا الأمر،
but most of them felt powerless to do anything about it --
ولكن معظمهم كان يشعر بعدم القدرة على فعل أي شيء --
until one group of citizens, just 12 regular people,
إلى أن قامت مجموعة من المواطنين، اثنا عشر شخصًا اعتياديًا فقط،
put out a call on Facebook to their friends
أطلقوا نداءً لأصدقائهم على فيسبوك
to meet in the central plaza, holding signs with a message:
ليتقابلوا في الميدان العام المركزي، حاملين لافتات تقول:
"Renuncia YA" --
"Renuncia YA" --
resign already.
تنحُّوا الآن.
To their surprise,
ما فاجأهم هو
30,000 people showed up.
ظهور ثلاثين ألفًا من الناس.
They stayed there for months as protests spread throughout the country.
ظلوا هنالك لشهور بينما تنتشر الاحتجاجات خلال البلاد.
At one point,
وصل الأمر إلى أن
the organizers delivered hundreds of eggs to various government buildings
المنظمين جلبوا مئات من البيضات لمبانٍ حكومية مختلفة
with a message:
مكتوب عليها:
"If you don't have the huevos" --
"إن لم يكن لديكم الـhuevos"
the balls --
أي الشجاعة --
"to stop corrupt candidates from running for office,
"لمنع المرشحين الفاسدين من الترشح للمنصب
you can borrow ours."
يمكنكم استعارتها منا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
President Molina responded
رد الرئيس (مولينا)
by vowing that he would never step down.
بأن تعهد أنه لن يتنازل أبدًا.
And the activists realized that they couldn't just keep protesting
أدرك الناشطون أنهم لا يمكن أن يكتفوا بالاحتجاج
and ask the president to resign.
وطلب التنحي من الرئيس؛
They needed to leave him no choice.
كان عليهم أن لا يتركوا له خيارًا آخر،
So they organized a general strike,
لذلك نظموا إضرابًا عامًّا،
in which people throughout the country refused to work.
حيث رفض أشخاص في كل أنحاء البلاد أن يعملوا.
In Guatemala City alone,
في مدينة جواتيمالا فقط
over 400 businesses and schools shut their doors.
أكثر من أربعمائة مكان عمل ومدرسة أغلقوا أبوابهم.
Meanwhile,
في الوقت نفسه
farmers throughout the country blocked major roads.
أغلق مزارعون طرقًا عموميةً في كل أنحاء البلاد.
Within five days,
في خلال خمسة أيام،
the president,
الرئيس،
along with dozens of other government officials,
بجانب عشرات من المسؤولين الحكوميين،
resigned already.
تنحوا بالفعل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I've been greatly inspired
أُلهمت بشكل عظيم
by the creativity and bravery of people using nonviolent action
بإبداع وشجاعة من يستخدمون الصراع السلمي
in nearly every country in the world.
في جميع بلدان العالم تقريبًا.
For example,
على سبيل المثال:
recently a group of activists in Uganda
مؤخرًا قامت مجموعة من النشطاء في أوغندا
released a crate of pigs in the streets.
بإطلاق قطيع من الخنازير في الشوارع.
You can see here that the police are confused about what to do with them.
يمكنك أن ترى هنا أن الشرطة في حيرة عما ينبغي أن تفعله بهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The pigs were painted the color of the ruling party.
كانت الخنازير قد تم طلاؤها بنفس لون الحزب الحاكم،
One pig was even wearing a hat,
وكان هناك خنزير يرتدي قبعة،
a hat that people recognized.
قبعة كان يعرفها الناس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Activists around the world are getting better at grabbing headlines,
النشطاء حول العالم صاروا يجيدون تصدر عناوين الصحف،
but these isolated actions do very little
ولكن هذه الأفعال المنعزلة ليس لها تأثير كبير
if they're not part of a larger strategy.
لو لم تكن جزءًا من استراتيجية أكبر.
A general wouldn't march his troops into battle
لن يقود جنرال قواته إلى معركة
unless he had a plan to win the war.
إن لم يكن لديه خطة لكسب الحرب.
Yet this is how most of the world's nonviolent movements operate.
لكن هكذا تعمل معظم التحركات السلمية في العالم.
Nonviolent struggle is just as complex as military warfare,
النضال السلمي معقد، تمامًا كالحروب العسكرية،
if not more.
إن لم يكن أكثر.
Its participants must be well-trained and have clear objectives,
لابد للمشاركين فيه أن يتم تدريبهم جيدًا، وأن يكون لهم أهداف وضحة،
and its leaders must have a strategy of how to achieve those objectives.
ولابد لقادتهم أن يكون لهم استراتيجية تمكنهم من الوصول لأهدافهم.
The technique of war has been developed over thousands of years
أساليب الحرب تم تطويرها على مر آلاف من السنين
with massive resources
عن طريق موارد هائلة
and some of our best minds dedicated to understanding
وعدد من أفضل العقول تم تكريسها لفهم
and improving how it works.
وتحسين كيفية عملها.
Meanwhile, nonviolent struggle is rarely systematically studied,
بينما النضال السلمي نادرًا ما يتم دراسته بشكل منهجي،
and even though the number is growing,
وعلى الرغم من زيادة العدد المستمرة،
there are still only a few dozen people in the world who are teaching it.
لايزال هنالك القليل من الأشخاص الذين يدرسونه في العالم.
This is dangerous,
هذ خطر؛
because we now know that our old approaches of dealing with conflict
لأننا الآن نعلم أن طرقنا القديمة للتعامل مع الصراعات
are not adequate for the new challenges that we're facing.
لم تعد مناسبة للتحديات الجديدة التي نواجهها.
The US government recently admitted
اعترفت الحكومة الأمريكية مؤخرًا
that it's in a stalemate in its war against ISIS.
أنها في مأزق في حربها ضد داعش.
But what most people don't know
لكن أغلب الناس لا يعلمون
is that people have stood up to ISIS using nonviolent action.
أن الناس وقفوا ضد داعش مستخدمين انضال السلمي.
When ISIS captured Mosul in June 2014,
عندما أسرت داعش مدينة الموصل في يونيو 2014،
they announced that they were putting in place a new public school curriculum,
أعلنوا أنهم سيضعون منهجًا دراسيًا جديدًا
based on their own extremist ideology.
مبنيًا على أيديولوجيتهم المتطرفة؛
But on the first day of school,
لكن في أول يوم دراسي
not a single child showed up.
لم يذهب طفل واحد.
Parents simply refused to send them.
ببساطة، رفض الآباء إرسالهم،
They told journalists they would rather homeschool their children
وأخبروا الصحفيين أنهم يفضلون تعليم أطفالهم في المنزل
than to have them brainwashed.
على أن يتم غسيل دماغهم.
This is an example of just one act of defiance
هذا مثال لتحرك متحدٍّ واحد فقط
in just one city.
في مدينة واحدة فقط.
But what if it was coordinated
ولكن ماذا لو تم تنظيمه
with the dozens of other acts of nonviolent resistance
مع العشرات من تحركات المقاومة السلمية
that have taken place against ISIS?
التي تم اتخاذها ضد داعش؟
What if the parents' boycott was part of a larger strategy
ماذا لو أن مقاطعة الآباء كانت جزءًا من استراتيجية أكبر
to identify and cut off the resources that ISIS needs to function;
لتحديد وقطع الموارد التي تحتاجها داعش للعمل؛
the skilled labor needed to produce food;
العمالة المدربة التي تحتاجها لإنتاج الطعام،
the engineers needed to extract and refine oil;
والمهندسين المكلفين باستخراج البترول وتكريره،
the media infrastructure and communications networks
والبنية التحتية للإعلام ووسائل التواصل،
and transportation systems,
وأنظمة التنقل،
and the local businesses that ISIS relies on?
والأعمال المحلية التي تعتمد عليها داعش؟
It may be difficult to imagine defeating ISIS
ربما يبدو من الصعب هزيمة داعش
with action that is nonviolent.
باستخدام تحركات سلمية؛
But it's time we challenge the way we think about conflict
لكن الوقت قد حان لاعتراض طريقة تفكيرنا تجاه الصراع،
and the choices we have in facing it.
وما لدينا من خيارات لمواجهته.
Here's an idea worth spreading:
هاكم فكرة تستحق الانتشار:
let's learn more about where nonviolent action has worked
هيا بنا نتعلم المزيد عن أينما نجح النضال السلمي
and how we can make it more powerful,
وكيف يمكننا جعله أقوى،
just like we do with other systems and technologies
تمامًا كما نفعل مع الأنظمة والتكنولوجيا
that are constantly being refined to better meet human needs.
التي يتم دائمًا تنقيحها لتستوفي -بشكل أفضل- احتياجات البشر.
It may be that we can improve nonviolent action
ربما يمكنا تطوير النضال السلمي
to a point where it is increasingly used in place of war.
حتى يتم استخدامه بشكل متزايد بدلًا من الحرب.
Violence as a tool of conflict could then be abandoned
حينها يمكن أن يتم هجر العنف كوسيلة للصراع،
in the same way that bows and arrows were,
كما تم هجر الأقواس والأسهم،
because we have replaced them with weapons that are more effective.
لأننا استبدلنا بهم أسلحة أكثر فاعلية.
With human innovation, we can make nonviolent struggle more powerful
بالإبداع البشري يمكننا أن نجعل النضال السلمي أقوى
than the newest and latest technologies of war.
من أحدث تكنولوجيات الحرب.
The greatest hope for humanity lies not in condemning violence
أمل البشرية الأعظم لا يكمن في شجب العنف،
but in making violence obsolete.
بل في جعله بائدًا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)